A Guide to the J. Ambler Johnston Papers, 1900-1974
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
J. Ambler Johnston Papers, 1900-1974
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1974-012
9.0 cu. ft.; 9 boxes
The J. Ambler Johnston Papers include materials relating to his many activities, with a particular emphasis on Civil War Round Tables and Virginia Tech. Materials consist of correspondence, publications and ephemera, organizational and committee reports, and photographs.
Johnston, J. Ambler (James Ambler), 1885-1974
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The J. Ambler Johnston was donated to Special Collections in 1974.
Biographical Note
J. Ambler Johnston (1885-1974), architectural engineer, Civil War historian, and civic benefactor, graduate from VPI in 1904 with B.S and in 1905 with an M.E. In 1906, he received another M.E. from Cornell University and became co-founder of the architectural firm of Carneal and Johnston in Richmond, Virginia.
Carneal and Johnston was responsible for many buildings on the campuses of the University of Richmond (which later awarded Johnston an honorary D.Sc.), VPI, and VMI. Johnston helped rewrite Richmond's building code, was a charter member of the Richmond Rotary Club, and helped found a Civil War Round Table (CWRT) at the State Penitentiary. During World War I, Johnston served with the Richmond Light Infantry Blues (Home Guard). He held offices in several history and science-related organizations, including the Sons of the Revolution, the Society of the Cincinnatus, the Sons of Confederate Veterans, the Association for the Protection of Virginia Antiquities (APVA), the Descendants of the Signers of the Declaration of Independence, the Virginia Historical Society, and the Virginia Institute for Scientific Research.
A native of Rockbridge County, Virginia, Johnston was the son of a Civil War veteran. For more than forty years, he was closely associated with Douglas Southall Freeman, noted Civil War author. Both men owned land on which a number of Civil War battles were fought and later donated these lands to the National Park Service. After Freeman's death in 1953, Johnston often presented on the life of his fellow historian. His lecture tours earned him honorary membership in CWRTs in Kansas City, Chicago, Louisville, New York City, the Confederate Historical Society of England, and Richmond. In 1965, he served as chairman of the Richmond Civil War Centennial Committee.
Throughout his life, Johnston maintained close ties with Virginia Tech. He served as president of the Alumni Association, received the 1961 Distinguished Alumni Citation and had a dormitory building named after him in 1966. He lived in Richmond until his death in 1974.
Scope and Content
The J. Ambler Johnston Papers include materials relating to his many activities, with a particular emphasis on Civil War Round Tables and Virginia Tech. Materials consist of correspondence, publications and ephemera, organizational and committee reports, and photographs.
Arrangement
Materials in the collection are arranged by subject matter. Within each topic, materials are arranged in chronological order.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
The J. Ambler Johnston collection of Civil War maps were separated to the Special Collections Historical Map Collection.
A model sculpture of Sacrifice, one of the Pylon statues in the War Memorial Court, was separated to the Artifact Collection.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Civil War; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865; University Archives
Organizations:
Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Contents List
- Civil War Centennial Commission, 1956-1958 (Box 1)
- Civil War Round Table, 1959-June 1960 (Box 1)
- Civil War Round Table, July 1960-October 1961 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes information on Stuart's ride around McClellan, 1862.
- Civil War Round Table, November 1961-April 1963 (Box 1)
  Includes information on the establishment of the Prison CWRT in Richmond.
- Civil War Round Table, May 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  Includes Distinguished Service Award to Prison CWRT.
- Civil War Round Table, 1965 (Box 1)
  Includes information on the CWRT's 25th anniversary; JAJ talk on Douglas S. Freeman.
- Civil War Round Table, January-August 1966 (Box 1)
  Includes information on the history of the CWRT; tour of Booth's escape route; JAJ talk on Grant and Lee.
- Civil War Round Table, September 1966-April 1967 (Box 2)
  Includes information on ceremonies at Fort Harrison.
- Civil War Round Table, May-December 1967 (Box 2)
  Includes information on the Appomattox parole of JAJ's father, Nathaniel Burwell Johnston.
- Civil War Round Table, January-June 1968 (Box 2)
  Includes JAJ talk on Robert E. Lee; JAJ talk "Then It Was Over."
- Civil War Round Table, July 1968-February 1969 (Box 2)
- Civil War Round Table, March-August 1969 (Box 2)
- Civil War Round Table, September 1969-April 1970 (Box 2)
- Civil War Round Table, May 1970-April 1971 (Box 2)
- Civil War Round Table, May 1971-April 1972 (Box 3)
- Civil War Round Table, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
- Maryland campaign of 1862 along with the routes of Lee and Jackson (notebook); Battle of Sharpsburg or Antietam (notes and scrapbook by C. k. Ragan) (Box 3)
- Battle of Elkhorn Tavern or Pea Ridge, 1862 (notebook by C. K. Ragan); unveiling of Jackson statue, 1875; trip to Cedar Mountain and Manassa Battlefield, 1960-968; Confederate Museum, 1960-1968; First Manassas and Second Manassas or Bull Run (Box 3)
- Richmond Civil War Centennial Commission, 1965-1972 (Box 3)
  Includes correspondence, brochures, and other publications by local, state, and national Civil War commissions.
- Douglas Southall Freeman, 1932-1957, 1960s (Box 3)
  Correspondence with, talks about, etc.
- Salem Flying Artillery (Box 4)
  Includes copies of the muster roll of Salem Flying Artillery, 1864; newspaper clippings on the commemoration of the Battle of Hanging Rock; military record of JAJ's father, N. B. Johnston; notebook by N. B. Johnston detailing his experiences in the Civil War.
- Seven Days Campaign (Box 4)
  Includes talks by JAJ; newspaper clippings on campaigns in the Richmond area (1894) between N. B. Johnson and R. A. Holdaway, an officer of the Northern Army of Virginia; resolution at the death of Capt. William B. Newton, Fourth Virginia Cavalry (1863).
- Civil War Round Table periodicals, brochures, and pamphlets; photographs of individuals at Civil War sites (Box 4)
- Echoes of 1861-1961 (by JAJ)--Correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 4)
- The War Did Not End at Yorktown (by JAJ)--Correspondence, 1953-1954, 1971 (Box 4)
- Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, 1964-1972 (Box 4)
  Includes correspondence; programs; Jamestown Committee minutes; reports on the restoration of the John Marshall house.
- Jamestown Society, 1956-1972 (Box 4)
  Includes correspondence; newsletters; membership lists.
- Virginia Historical Society, 1964-1972 (Box 5)
  Includes minutes; correspondence; membership lists; draft of a history of the VHS by JAJ, 1972; correspondence on save the Manassas battlefield, 1969.
- Virginia Institute for Scientific Research, 1969-1972 (Box 5)
  Includes correspondence; minutes; financial statements; reports.
- Sons of the Revolution in the State of Virginia; Society of the Cincinnatus in the State of Virginia; Descendants of the Signers of the Declaration of Independence; Sons of Confederate Veterans, 1963-1972 (Box 6)
  Scope and Content
  Materials include correspondence; minutes; reports.
  Arrangement note
  The first part of the material in this group is arranged in chronological order, regardless of the organization; the second part is arranged alphabeticall by the name of the society.
- Virginia Polytechnic Institute, 1935-1953, 1965-1966 (Box 6)
  Includes speeches before alumni groups; dedication speech for five new dorms, including Ambler Johnston Hall in 1966.
- Virginia Polytechnic Institute, 1967 (Box 6)
  Includes information on a proposed alumni camp.
- Virginia Polytechnic Institute, 1968 (Box 6)
  Includes information on the "Old Guard" Reunion; interest in an "Alumni House."
- Virginia Polytechnic Institute, January-June 1969 (Box 6)
  Includes information on the Alumni Fund Committee; dedication of Robeson Hall; photos of Ambler Johnston Hall.
- Virginia Polytechnic Institute, July-December 1969 (Box 7)
  Includes information on the proposed name change to Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University.
- Virginia Polytechnic Institute, January-August 1970 (Box 7)
  Includes information on a proposed history of VPI and VMI PWA projects.
- Virginia Polytechnic Institute, September 1970-1971 (Box 7)
  Includes information on student disruptions on VPI campus.
- Virginia Polytechnic Institute, 1972-1973, January 1974 (Box 7)
  Includes information on the Diamond Club bar.
- VPI History Department, 1901-1972 (Bulk 1967-1972) (Box 7)
  Includes correspondence on a research fund for Virginia history; encouraging research on the routes of the western migration through Southwest Virginia; first annual Civil War seminar, 1972. JAJ's recollections of his student days at VPI are included with June 1972 correspondence. Also included are JAJ's student diary, 1901, and a diary he kept while Alumni Association president, 1938-1940.
- Civil War Round Table annual tour portfolios, 1953-1973 (Box 7)
  Individual portfolios on the following tours include lists of participants, brochures, maps, and other publications relating to battlefield areas: Richmond (3rd), 1953; Central Tennessee (8th), 1958; Charleston and Savannah (9th), 1959; Gettysburg (12th), 1962; Louisiana (14th), 1964; Washington--Booth Trail (16th), 1966; Missouri and Arkansas (17th), 1967; Savannah and Charleston (20th), 1970; Stonewall Jackson's Valley Campaign (22nd), 1972; Kentucky Blue Grass (special tour), Fall 1972; Gettysburg--Carlisle (23rd), 1973.
- Recordings of talks by JAJ on Civil War subjects (Box 8)
  Includes 23 long playing records, c.1952-1966; 7 tapes, c.1957-1969; 3 cassettes; 34 dictaphone belts. Also includes plaques and awards given to JAJ by Civil War Round Tables.